Guide to the Chester H. McCall papers, 1931-1947
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center
Chester H. McCall papers
1931-1947
C0098
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center.
1.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
The Chester H. McCall papers contain materials from McCall's tenure at the U.S. Department of Commerce as well as his private life.
McCall, Chester H.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Unknown donor.
Biographical Information
Chester H. McCall served as Assistant Secretary of Commerce (1933-1937) under Daniel C. Roper in the Franklin D. Roosevelt Administration. While in the Department of Commerce, McCall headed up the administrative, public relations, and publications efforts of the department's Bureau of Foreign and Domestic Commerce, National Bureau of Standards, and Bureau of Air Commerce. He was also a member of the Executive Board of the National Youth Administration, secretary of several Cabinet committees, and represented Commerce in several inter-departmental committees.
Scope and Content
The Chester McCall Papers contain materials from his tenure at the Department of Commerce as well as his private life. The materials include correspondence between Chester McCall, Secretary Roper, government employees, and business leaders; speech drafts: "Credit and the New Deal" (March 13, 1934), "Regimentation and Recovery" (November 6, 1934), "Trading for Peace" (August 16, 1934); and contemporary news clippings regarding the Roosevelt Administration and the Department of Commerce. The materials also include documents and writings pertaining to McCall's personal life, memoranda and a handwritten note from Franklin D. Roosevelt.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by subject.
Related Material
Special Collections Research Center also holds many other collections on United States government and politics, particularly the Legislative branch. The include documents on the FDIC during the 1930s.
The University of Virginia Libraries also holds a collection of the.
Index Terms
Persons:
Maberry, Arthur; McCall, Chester H.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Roper, Daniel C. (Daniel Calhoun), 1867-1943
Corporate Names:
United States. Dept. of Commerce.
Subjects:
1930s; 1940s.; Educational change; International trade; Interstate commerce.; New Deal, 1933-1939.; United States--Politics and government
Contents List
- Letter from Hardin B. Arledge to D. C. Roper (Secretary of Commerce), January 2, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Letter to Leo Bouchard (Dayton Association of Credit Men), March 5, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence between McCall and Frank W. Boykin (House of Representatives), June 15-16, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence between McCall and Harry Brody, April 13,17, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence between McCall and Robert J. Bulkley (Senator), October-December, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence between McCall and Lawrence Calvert, June, September, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence between McCall and Ward Canaday, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence between McCall and Royal S. Copeland (Senator) - related materials in 2.2, October 5, 16, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence between McCall and Robert Cromie; newsclipping - "The Age of Youth" from The Vancouver Sun, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence between McCall and Clarence Francis - related correspondence and related newsclipping, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence between McCall and Alfred Friendly, June, September, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence between McCall and Reuben A. Lewis, August 1935 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence between McCall and Wayne Mendenhall, February 15, 1935, May 5, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence between McCall and Leonard C. Sauer - related newsclipping, April, May 1936 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Letter from E. R. Stettinius, Jr. to McCall, January 6, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Letter from McCall to Howard Tewksbury, May 5, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence between Daniel C. Roper and Harry S. Truman, September 1935 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Letter from Daniel Willard to Daniel C. Roper and related correspondence, May, June, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Documents from the Business Advisory and Planning Council for the Department of Commerce - related correspondence including memorandum from Franklin D. Roosevelt, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- "Credit and the New Deal" - an address by McCall before the Washington Association of Credit Men, March 13, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Memorandum from McCall to "The Secretary" in reference to the National Institution of Public Affairs, March 23, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Memorandum from McCall to Daniel C. Roper in reference to the Shipping Board Bureau and related letter, February 27, May 9, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- "Regimentation and Recovery" - an address by Daniel C. Roper over nation-wide network of the National Broadcasting Company, November 1934 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- "Trading for Peace" - an analytical study by McCall - part 1 of 3, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- "Trading for Peace" - an analytical study by McCall and newsclippings - part 2 of 3, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- "Trading for Peace" - an analytical study by McCall and related correspondence - part 3 of 3, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- "Forward with the Constitution" - an address by Daniel C. Roper on Constitution Day - related correspondence, documents, and newsclippings - part 1 of 2, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- "Forward with the Constitution" - an address by Daniel C. Roper on Constitution Day - related correspondence, documents, and newsclippings - part 2 of 2, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- "Report to the President of the United States on National Recovery and Employment" - report by the Durable Goods Industries Committee and related note, May 14, 1934, September 15, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- "Government article" pertaining to Federal Trade Commission and civil liberties - related newsclippings - personal writings, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Documents and correspondence related to planning of the Maberry Organization-correspondence between McCall and Arthur Maberry-related newsclippings, 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- memoranda between Daniel C. Roper and Franklin D. Roosevelt - related correspondence, 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Cabinet meeting memoranda from McCall to Daniel C. Roper - press release from Federal Emergency Administration of Public Works, 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence between John H. Overton and Johnston Avery on Bureau of Foreign and Domestic Commerce hiring - letter of recommendation by McCall for Ralph H. Michael, Jr., May 1935, April 1936 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- 16-A - "Report on Visit to the United States of America" (access copies) - letter from Thomas A.Watson to Daniel C. Roper - letter to John H. Love, October 30, 1925, September 27, 1934, March 29, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- "Kee-Notes" - keynoted activities of the Kiwanis Club of Bethesda, Maryland and souvenir calendars, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Newsclippings related to McCall's career and persona life in Bethesda, Maryland, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- "Editorship of Journal" - McCall's personal recollections of events leading to his becoming editor and publisher of the "Bethesda Journal" - related document, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- "Dark Stairs" - play script by unknown author - part 1 of 2, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- "Methods for Men, Money, Management and Government"-a report to Franklin D. Roosevelt from the Home Building Program of the Committee for Economic Recovery-related documents and newsclippings, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Handwritten note from Franklin D. Roosevelt (includes access copy), circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Untitled play by unknown author-part 1 of 3, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Untitled play by unknown author-part 2 of 3-letter to McCall from Charles H. Smith, undated and 1931 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Untitled play by unknown author-part 3 of 3, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Letters from National Aeronautic Association-letter from the Air Defense League and associated document, January-February, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Memorandum to Daniel C. Roper on commercial attache to USSR and related newsclipping-document on trade with Cuba-anonymous memorandum to McCall, 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Personal recollections of Daniel C. Roper by Daniel J. Currie-related document, December 5, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Mission statement for the National Institution of Public Affairs-related newsclippings and document, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- "Dark Stairs"-play script by unknown author-part 2 of 2, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Writings by Mickey McCall-related photograph, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Notebook with handwritten notes and inserts-related newsclippings-envelopes from the Department of Commerce-preservation note: two rusted paper clips attached to materials, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Notebook with handwritten notes and inserts, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- "Space and Time" newsletter referencing McCall's business activities after departure from Washington, D.C., February 20, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- "The Psychological Cycle" essay by unknown author-letter to McCall from H. E. Waterbury-telegram from E. L. Sweek with handwritten note-, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 6)